After two years of pandemic emergency,
could 2022 be the year the world
finally learned to live with COVID-19?
From Asia to Africa,
countries re-opened for business and visitors
following developments in COVID-19 vaccination and treatment.
On New Year's Day, Portugal's President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa
announced the easing of COVID-19 restrictions.
He said his country had "moved
into the endemic" period of the pandemic.
Endemic means a disease
has settled in a place for years to come.
Britain's Prime Minister at the time, Boris Johnson,
took similar action later that month.
Announcing an end to requirements for face coverings,
he said, "We will trust the judgment of the British people
and no longer criminalize anyone
who chooses not to wear one."
The moves were the start of re-opening borders
to members of the European Union
and then to vaccinated travelers from around the world.
Australian officials, however,
denied entry to Novak Djokovic,
the world's top tennis player, in January.
The country's health officials ruled that Djokovic
failed to meet the country's vaccination requirement.
The World Health Organization (WHO) added in January
that countries could consider easing COVID rules
if they had high vaccination rates
and strong healthcare systems.
In June, South Africa lifted its COVID restrictions.
Visitors can come and go
without vaccination papers or testing.
Other African countries including Madagascar,
Egypt, and Botswana soon followed.
Many Asian countries opened back up in 2022 as well.
Thailand, Vietnam, India, Japan, South Korea,
and Indonesia all eased restrictions and welcomed visitors.
In the State of the Union speech to Congress in March,
American President Joe Biden said,
"Last year COVID-19 kept us apart.
This year we are finally together again."
He noted that the gathering did not require face coverings.
That was possible, he said in his speech,
because of the progress in vaccine
and anti-viral treatment efforts.
As the Omicron version of the virus
was quickly spreading around the world,
United States health officials approved the first drug
against COVID-19 that could be taken at home.
The drug, Paxlovid, is a pill
made by the U.S. drug company Pfizer.
All the earlier approved drugs against COVID
require injection directly
into the blood by healthcare professionals.
Pfizer made Paxlovid available
at low prices to the poorest countries.
Dr. Gregory Poland of the Mayo Clinic in Minnesota
spoke about Paxlovid at the time.
He said: "You're looking at a 90 percent decreased risk
of hospitalization and death in a high-risk group..."
The high-risk group includes older people
and those with conditions like
being severely overweight or having heart disease.
In August, U.S. health officials approved new vaccines
made by Pfizer-BioNTech and Moderna.
The new shots are called "bivalent."
They are designed to protect against both the earliest
and newer versions of Omicron called BA.4 and BA.5.
The approval of the updated vaccines
is the first step toward dealing with COVID-19 vaccine updates
in the same way as yearly flu shots.
In this case, health officials ordered vaccine makers
to make changes and to target the latest coronavirus versions
without depending on human testing.
The U.S. was not the only country
with plans to update COVID-19 vaccines.
Health officials in Britain and other European countries
also offered "bivalent" shots
to target different versions of the virus.
I'm Caty Weaver.
And I'm Mario Ritter Jr.